A Guide to the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities records, 1890-1974
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities records, 1890-1974
The Library of Virginia
32900
42 volumes
Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, 2300 East Grace Street, Richmond, Virginia 23223.
Alternative Form Available
For preservation purposes, please serve microfilm (Misc. reels 6028-6047).
Historical Information
The Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities (APVA) was founded in 1889 in Williamsburg, Virginia, to preserve and restore deteriorating historical sites in Virginia. The APVA bought the site where Jamestown is located. Over the years the organization (recently renamed Preservation Virginia) has worked with public and private groups to restore sites. The group owns several sites in the state that are open to the public, including Bacon's Castle and the Cape Henry Lighthouse.
Scope and Content
Records, 1890-1974, of the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities (now Preservation Virginia) consisting of minute books, record books, secretary's books, financial records and ledgers, Jamestown visitors registers, and scrapbooks detailing the activities and goals of the APVA.
Minute books include record book, 1896-1917, of the Washington Branch of the APVA containing applications, clippings, member lists, minutes, reports, and rules; and minute book, 1934-1944, of the Powhatan Hill Memorial Association consisting of articles, clippings, correspondence, lists, and minutes. Secretary's book, 1897-1899, contains accounts, list of letters written, and other papers. General Endowment Fund, life members, 1930-1957, includes accounts and correspondence concerning contributions to the APVA.
Ledgers, 1894-1950, contain accounts; expenses and receipts; lists of officers and members; payment of dues, and other records concerning the finances of the APVA. Jamestown Visitors Registers, 1901-1939 and part of 1941, contains the names of visitors and listing their residences. Scrapbooks, 1890-1974, consist of articles, booklets, brochures, bulletins, clippings, correspondence, flyers, lists, maps, newsletters, photographs, poems, programs, and other papers concerning the goals, operations, and programs of the APVA, including information on properties the organization owned. Of special interest is a scrapbook for the 350th anniversary of the settlement of Jamestown. There are also two blank scrapbooks.
Contents List
- Minute books, record books, ledgers, registers, and scrapbooks, 1890-1974., Extent: 20 reels. (Reel 6028-6047)
  - Washington D.C. Branch record book, 1896-1917 (Reel 6028)
  - Powhatan Hill Memorial Association minute book, 1934-1944 (Reel 6028)
  - Secretary's book, 1897-1899 (Reel 6028)
  - General endowment fund, life members, 1930-1957 (Reel 6028)
  - Ledger 1, March 1894-December 1900 (Reel 6029)
  - Ledger 2, January 1901-June 1907 (Reel 6029)
  - Ledger 3, July 1907-December 1923 (Reel 6029)
  - Ledger 4, January 1924-June 1935 (Reel 6030)
  - Ledger 5, July 1935-October 1941 (Reel 6030)
  - Ledger 6, November 1941-December 1947 (Reel 6030)
  - Ledger 7, January 1948-December 1950 (Reel 6030)
  - Jamestown Visitors Register, June 1901-April 1907 (Reel 6031)
  - Jamestown Visitors Register, May 1907-January 1916 (Reel 6031)
  - Jamestown Visitors Register, January 1916-July 1925 (Reel 6031)
  - Jamestown Visitors Register, August 1925-September 1928 (Reel 6032)
  - Jamestown Visitors Register, September 1928-April 1930 (Reel 6033)
  - Jamestown Visitors Register, April 1930-August 1930 (Reel 6033)
  - Jamestown Visitors Register, August 1930-June 1931 (Reel 6033)
  - Jamestown Visitors Register, June 1931-October 1931 (Reel 6034)
  - Jamestown Visitors Register, October 1931-July 1932 (Reel 6034)
  - Jamestown Visitors Register, July 1932-June 1933 (Reel 6034)
  - Jamestown Visitors Register, June 1933-July 1934 (Reel 6034)
  - Jamestown Visitors Register, July 1934-November 1935 (Reel 6035)
  - Jamestown Visitors Register, November 1935-October 1936 (Reel 6035)
  - Jamestown Visitors Register, October 1936-June 1937 (Reel 6035)
  - Jamestown Visitors Register, June 1937-April 1938 (Reel 6036)
  - Jamestown Visitors Register, April 1938-April 1939 (Reel 6036)
  - Jamestown Visitors Register, April 1939-November 1939 (Reel 6036)
  - Jamestown Visitors Register, June 1941-September 1941 (Reel 6036)
  - Scrapbook, 1890-1949 (Reel 6037)
  - Scrapbook, 1950-1953 (Reel 6038)
  - Scrapbook, 1954-1956 (Reel 6039)
  - Scrapbook, January-August 1957 (Reel 6040)
  - Scrapbook, 350th Anniversary of Jamestown's settlement, 1957 (Reel 6041)
  - Scrapbook, 1957-1959 (Reel 6042)
  - Scrapbook, 1959-1962 (Reel 6043)
  - Scrapbook, 1963-1966 (Reel 6044)
  - Scrapbook, 1966-1968 (Reel 6045)
  - Scrapbook, 1966-1969 (Reel 6046)
  - Scrapbook, 1970-1974 (Reel 6047)
  - Scrapbook, blank, no date
  - Scrapbook, blank, no date